Finding Aid for Alpha Phi Omega, Gamma Pi Chapter. (University of Michigan) publications, 1964-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alpha Phi Omega, Gamma Pi Chapter. (University of Michigan) publications, 1964-2007 1964-2007, 1986-2003
Alpha Phi Omega. Gamma Pi Chapter (University of Michigan)
0.75 linear feet
0364 Fimu 2
Alpha Phi Omega is a national service fraternity. This collection of publications from the Gamma Pi chapter at the University of Michigan includes a guide to the university created by the fraternity, chapter newsletters, many issues of the chapter's biannual publication Pi Filling, and several programs from the fraternity's banquets.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from Alpha Phi Omega (Donor No. 8222 ) in 1994, 1999, and 2011.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The history of the Gamma Pi chapter of the national service fraternity of Alpha Phi Omega (APO) is one of commitment to the founding principles of fellowship, leadership and service, and reflects the organization's responses to the changing service needs of a large, dynamic university as well as to larger societal mandates for a broadened interpretation of equal opportunity.
On November 2, 1939, a meeting of the Rover Boy Scout group was held at the student union to discuss the formation of a pledge group for a local chapter of Alpha Phi Omega. A year later, members of the pledge group, primarily Rover Scouts, were initiated by APO chapter members from Michigan State University to officially form the Gamma Pi chapter. The national organization had been founded in 1925, in part to provide former boy scouts a college organization based on scouting principles. The bylaws described the purpose of the fraternity as, "to assemble college students in a National Service Fraternity in the fellowship of the principles of the Boy Scouts of America as embodied in its Scout Oath and Law, to develop Leadership, to promote Friendship, and provide Service to humanity."
As a chapter of APO, Gamma Pi had some flexibility in administration of its local programs and activities. Structurally it belonged to Section 54 consisting of the state of Michigan, which was part of a larger Region 6 comprised of Illinois, Indiana, and Michigan, all under the governance of an elected national Board of Directors. Leadership and fellowship opportunities were available at meetings of all three hierarchical levels, and service project ideas and experiences were widely shared.
In October 1970, Gamma Pi chapter proposed language changes in the national bylaws to support membership status for women. Despite an appeal led by the national organization to exclude APO from Title IX ruling, the United States Department of Health Education and Welfare found in 1976 that APO's membership practices were subject to the provisions of Title IX. Full membership opportunities must now be extended to women if university sponsorship were to continue. Women's names appear on the membership roster of Gamma Pi beginning in 1976.
Pledges to APO were invited twice yearly and became full members after demonstrating an understanding of APO history and goals and after performing required service hours.
Gamma Pi's service projects changed from year to year and from decade to decade and included conducting fingerprinting for FBI civilian identification files, soliciting donations for charitable causes, giving campus tours, staffing the student union lounge, ushering at campus events, counting ballots, maintaining an exam file, helping move books at the public library, making recordings for foreign students, and selling student directories. Ongoing projects included providing copy service at cost, distributing and posting campus signs, and sponsoring a yearly blood drive competition with Ohio State University.
The Alpha Phi Omega publications collection has been divided into four series: Handbook, Newsletters, Pi Filling, and Programs.
Subjects:
Alpha Phi Omega. Gamma Pi Chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.--Periodicals.; University of Michigan--Students.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Piece of pi.; Gamma pi a la mode.; Gamma pi filling.
Genre Terms:
Newsletters.
- Handbook
  The Handbook series contains a guide to the University of Michigan entitled Wolverine Handbook created by Alpha Phi Omega in 1964.
  - Wolverine Handbook 1964 (Box 1)
- Newsletters
  The Newsletters series includes several newsletters published by the fraternity A Piece of Pi and A La Mode.
  - A Piece of Pi, 1985 (Box 1)
  - A La Mode
    - 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1996-2004 (Box 1)
- Pi Filling
  The Pi Filling series composes the bulk of the collection and includes issues of Alpha Phi Omega's biannual publication. Pi Filling issues contain pledge blurbs, event photos, and a variety of other information.
  - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - W 1987 (Box 1)
  - F 1987 (Box 1)
  - W 1988 (Box 1)
  - F 1989 (Box 1)
  - W 1990 (Box 1)
  - F 1990 (Box 1)
  - W 1991 (Box 1)
  - F 1991 (Box 1)
  - W 1992 (Box 1)
  - W 1993 (Box 1)
  - F 1993 (Box 1)
  - W 1994 (Box 1)
  - F 1995 (Box 1)
  - W 1996 (Box 1)
  - W 1997 (Box 1)
  - F 1997 (Box 1)
  - F 1998 (Box 1)
  - W 1999 (Box 1)
  - F 1999 (Box 1)
  - W 2000 (Box 1)
  - W 2001 (Box 1)
  - F 2001 (Box 1)
  - W 2002 (Box 1)
  - F 2002 (Box 1)
  - W 2003 (Box 1)
  - F 2003 (Box 1)
  - W 2004 (Box 1)
  - CDs 2004-2007 (Box 1)
- Programs
  The Programs series contains three programs for Alpha Phi Omega banquets from spring 1993, fall 1998, and fall 2003.
  - Banquet Programs 1993-2003 (Box 1)